

□ 216-544-8680 | 🗷 xliu330@asu.edu | 🧥 xiao-liu.me | 🖸 liuxiao1468 | 🛅 xiao-leo-liu-1a5bb3112

## Summary.

I am a senior Computer Science Ph.D student and I work with Prof. Heni Ben Amor at Interactive Robotics Lab in School of Computing and Augmented Intelligence at Arizona State University. My research is focusing Differentiable Bayesian Filters, Representation Learning, and their applications in Robot Learning and Human-robot Interaction (HRI). Several publications of my research are/were shown at ICRA, IROS, and CoRL. I also work as a Research Data Scientist for a Phoenix and Seattle based start-up company, RadiusAl.

### Education

**Arizona State University** Tempe, Arizona

Ph.D. in Computer Science, Advisor: Prof. Heni Ben Amor

Aug. 2019 - May. 2024 • Thesis Focus: Robot Learning with Differentiable Filters GPA: 4.0/4.0

**Case Western Reserve University** 

M.S. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING, ADVISOR: PROF. KIJU LEE Aug. 2016 - May. 2019

• Thesis Focus: Automated Facial Emotion Recognition for Human-Robot Interaction GPA: 3.8/4.0

**Southwest Jiaotong University** 

B.S. IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING Aug. 2011 - May. 2015

• Project: Fault Diagnosis of Roller Bearing Based on Wavelet Analysis GPA: 3.6/4.0

# **Experience**

RadiusAI, Inc. Tempe, Arizona

RESEARCH DATA SCIENTIST (PART-TIME)

Sep. 2020 - Present

- Refined Multi-object tracking (MOT) algorithms using Bayes Filter for Video Analytics for indoor and outdoor cameras, improved ~9% accuracy.
- · Developed multi-objective optimization technique base on Frank-Wolfe algorithm for training monocular depth prediction model across multiple datasets.
- Researched on monocular depth prediction models with varied advanced architecture, Vision Transformer and multi-scale local planar guidance blocks, achieved depth estimation with 0.117, 0.416 on abs REL and RMS error metrics and 0.868 on d1 metric on NYU depth testset.

**Interactive Robtoics Lab, ASU** Tempe, Arizona

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

June. 2020 - Present

- Created a multimodal learning framework (α-MDF) using attention mechanism and differentiable filtering, which conducts state estimation in latent space with multiple modalities. Experimented on real-world tasks and validated the system on both rigid body robots and soft robots. [C5]
- Developed differentiable Ensemble Kalman Filters (DEnKF) framework incorporating algorithmic priors for robot learning, i.e., learning system dynamics from observations, and learning representations from high-dimensional space. [C4]
- Proposed spatio-temporal enhancement module for DEnKF to ensure the generalized performance on real robot within nonlinear systems. [C3]
- Deployed the differentiable filtering framework for varied tasks, i.e., the KITTI visual odometry task, robot manipulation tasks using a UR5 arm, and the state estimation for tensegrity soft robot.
- Deployed the differentiable filtering framework with smartwatch for ubiquitous robot control tasks, i.e., remote teleoperation, drone piloting. [S1]

#### **Case Western Reserve University**

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Aug. 2017 - Aug. 2019

- · Led social robot project "Woody and Philos" project, developed advanced algorithms in Computer Vision for broad. [C2]
- · Real-time Human Facial Emotion Expression Recognition for Human-robot Interaction using deep learning and machine learning technique. (featured on Case Western Daily) [C1] [J1]
- · Developed social robots-"Philos" & "Woody" from the kinematics to the high-level control. Investigated the potential of social robots as cognitive assessment applications for clinical trials in Autism Spectrum Disorder & Alzheimer's. (featured on ideastream)
- Collaborated on hardware and algorithm development for the vision-based Tangible Geometric Games- "e-Cube" for cognitive skills assessment.

#### **Case Western Reserve University**

TEACHING ASSISTENT

Aug. 2018 - Aug. 2019

• Served as the teaching assistant for EMAE250 (Computers in Mechanical Engineering), conducting lab sessions twice a week. The responsibilities included instructing students on numerical problem-solving using Matlab and providing guidance throughout the learning process.

Uber Technologies, Inc. Xi'an, China

**DATA ANALYST**Jan. 2016 - Aug. 2016

· Coordinated data analysis and fraud detection with the operation team. Conducted competitor tracking and advising on driver incentives.

Hitachi, Ltd. Chengdu, China

DESIGN ENGINEER June 2015 - Dec. 2015

Assisted in product development by analyzing cable and power converter sizing, heat release, and power supply design. Revised design parameters
to meet customer requirements and national standards while optimizing manufacturing and logistical processes for cost reduction.

## **Publications**

2024	[\$1], Weigend, F, Liu, X, Sonawani, S & Ben Amor, H. "iRoCo: Intuitive Robot Control from Anywhere using a	ICRA 2024
2023	Smartwatch" IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), in review  [W2], Liu, X, Zhou, Y, Ikemoto, S & Ben Amor, H. "Multimodal Learning of Soft Robot Dynamics using	CoRL 2023
	Differentiable Filters" CoRL 2023 Workshop on Learning for Soft Robots	
2023 2023	[C5], $\underline{\text{Liu}}$ , $\underline{\text{X}}$ , $\underline{\text{Zhou}}$ , $\underline{\text{Y}}$ , $\underline{\text{Ikemoto}}$ , $\underline{\text{S}}$ & Ben Amor, $\underline{\text{H}}$ . " $\alpha$ -MDF: An Attention-based Multimodal Differentiable Filter for	CoRL 2023 IROS 2023
	Robot State Estimation" 7th Conference on Robot Learning  [W1] Weigend E. Liu, Y. & Ron Amer. H. "Drobabilistic Differentiable Filters Enable Ubiquitous Robot Control	
	[W1], Weigend, F, Liu, X, & Ben Amor, H. "Probabilistic Differentiable Filters Enable Ubiquitous Robot Control with Smartwatches" <i>IROS 2023 Workshop on Differentiable Probabilistic Robotics</i>	
2023	[C4], Liu, X, Clark, G, Campbell, J, Zhou, Y & Ben Amor, H. "Enhancing State Estimation in Robots: A Data-Driven	IROS 2023
	Approach with Differentiable Ensemble Kalman Filters" IEEE/RSJ IROS	
2023	[C3], Liu, X, Ikemoto, S, Yoshimitsu, Y & Ben Amor, H. "Learning Soft Robot Dynamics using Differentiable Kalman Filters and Spatio-Temporal Embeddings" <i>IEEE/RSJ IROS</i>	IROS 2023
2021	[J1], Liu, X, Cheng, X & Lee, K. "GA and SVM based Facial Emotion Recognition using Geometric Features" <i>IEEE</i>	IEEE sensors 2021
	sensors Journal on Machine Vision and automated systems	
2020	[C2], Hayosh D, Liu, X & Lee, K. "Woody: Low-Cost Open-source Humanoid Torso Robot" <i>IEEE 17th International</i>	UR 2020
	Conference on Ubiquitous Robots (UR)	
2020	[C1], Liu, X & Lee, K. "Optimized Facial Emotion Recognition Technique for Assessing User Experience" IEEE	GEM 2020
	Games Entertainment and Medias Conference (GEM)	

# **Skills**

• Programming: Python, C/C++, Java; Tools & Library: PyTorch, TensorFlow, OpenCV, ROS, Matlab, MuJoCo, Unity, Docker, Git, Kubernetes;

### References

Heni Ben Amor

Tempe, Arizona

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR, Ph.D. Advisor

Arizona State University

• School of Computing and Augmented Intelligence, Interactive Robotics Lab Tel: 480.965.2253, Email: hbenamor@asu.edu

Kiju Lee College Station, Texa

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR, M.S. ADVISOR

Texas A&M University

• Engineering Technology and Industrial Distribution and Mechanical Engineering Tel: 979.458.6479, Email: kiju.lee@tamu.edu

Wenlong Zhang
Mesa, Arizona

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR, Ph.D. COMMITTEE MEMBER

Arizona State University

• School of Manufacturing Systems and Networks at the Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering Email: Wenlong. Zhang@asu.edu

Aykut Dengi Tempe, Arizona

CEO, INDUSTRY ADVISOR RadiusAl

• Co-founder, Co-CEO, and Board Member, RadiusAl Tel: 480.540.1349, Email: aykut.dengi@radius.ai